From slave to criminal with one amendment.
13th is a documentary film directed by Ava DuVernay.
An in-depth look at the prison system in the United States and how it
reveals the nation's history of racial inequality.
Self, played by Jelani Cobb.
Self, played by Angela Davis.
Self, played by Henry Louis Gates, Jr..
Self, played by Michelle Alexander.
Self - U.S. Senator (D) New Jersey, played by Cory Booker.
Self, played by Marie Gottschalk.
13th is a 2016 American documentary film directed by Ava DuVernay.
It explores the prison–industrial complex, and the "intersection of race,
justice, and mass incarceration in the United States".
The title refers to the Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution, adopted in 1865, which abolished slavery
throughout the United States and ended involuntary servitude, except as punishment for convicted criminals.
The film argues that this exemption has been used to continue the
practice of involuntary servitude in the form of penal labor.
DuVernay contends that slavery in the United States has been perpetuated since the end of the Civil War through criminalizing behavior and enabling police to arrest poor freedmen and force them to work for the state under convict leasing; suppression of African Americans by
disenfranchisement, lynchings, and Jim Crow; politicians declaring a war on drugs that weighs more heavily on minority communities; and, by the late 20th century, mass incarceration affecting communities of color, especially American descendants of slavery.
In addition to the prison-industrial complex, the film examines the emerging detention-industrial
complex, discussing how much money is being made by corporations from such incarcerations.
The film garnered widespread critical acclaim.
It was nominated for the Academy Award for Best Documentary Feature at the 89th Academy Awards, and it won the
Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Documentary or Nonfiction Special at the 69th Primetime Emmy Awards.
The film explores themes of prison, politics, slavery, race politics, murder.